Finding Aid for George Meader Papers 1922-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George Meader Papers 1922-1990, 1943-1966
Meader, George, 1907-
1 oversize folders
42 linear feet
Ann Arbor, Michigan attorney, counsel to U.S. Congressional committees, and Republican Congressman, 1951-1965. Correspondence files concerning work with the Senate Committee Investigating the National Defense Program after World War II, and Congressional files, especially concerning his work with the House Judiciary Committee and the House Committee on Government Operations; also photographs and motion picture films.
851811 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
George Meader (donor no. 5226 ) donated his papers in a series of accessions beginning in 1968.
The collection is open for research.
George Meader served as United States Congressman, 1951-1964, for the second congressional district of southeastern Michigan. In the 1950s, this district encompassed parts of Jackson, Lenawee, Monroe, and Washtenaw counties. After the 1962 redistricting, Meader represented the citizens of parts of Jackson, Lenawee, Livington, Washtenaw, and Wayne counties. In 1950, the Republican Meader easily won the seat that had long been held by Earl Michener, another Republican. Meader handily won the next six Congressional elections, his narrowest margin of victory being 23,000 votes. In 1964, he narrowly lost his seat to the liberal Democrat, Weston Vivian, who rode the coattails of Johnson's landslide. Meader attempted to regain the office in 1966, but his bid for reelection failed when he lost the Republican primary to Marvin Esch.
Meader was born in Benton Harbor, Michigan on September 13, 1907, and was educated in Michigan schools. He worked his way through the University of Michigan, graduating with honors from the Literary College in 1927, and receiving his Juris Doctor degree from the Law School in 1931. Meader's affiliation with the university continued as he served as president of the University of Michigan Club of Ann Arbor and as vice-president of the Alumni Association. Upon graduation from law school, he set up shop as a practicing attorney in Ann Arbor in 1932. In 1939 he served as counsel for the Michigan Merit System Association where he directed the campaign that replaced the spoils systems for state employees with a civil service system. In 1940, Meader was elected prosecuting attorney for Washtenaw County, a post he capably filled until 1943.
During World War II Meader served for four years as the counsel for the Senate's National Defense Investigating Committee (the Truman Committee). This committee looked into military supply and defense industries to assure that full energies were given to the war effort and that no corruption existed. Meader's enthusiastic work as counsel on this committee set the tone for his ensuing work in Washington, D. C. In 1948 he was appointed counsel for the Senate Banking and Currency Subcommittee Investigating Reconstruction Finance Corporation loans. Meader's commitment to battling corruption and to clean government continued to be evident during his Congressional service.
In 1950 Meader won the Republican primary contest of six candidates, and defeated the Democratic candidate J. P. Dawson by over 20,000 votes. Due to his experience on the Truman and RFC committees, Meader was named to the Committee on Government Operations and its subcommittees on Government Information and Foreign Operations. In fulfilling these committee obligations, Meader aimed at economy and intelligence in government activities. He sought to increase efficiency in executive bureaus and agencies, to improve the investigative functions of Congressional committees, and to make public hearings accessible to radio and television reporting. Meader also encouraged reduction of federal foreign aid by promoting self-help and the overseas investment of private capital. In his fifth term in Congress, Meader was named to the Committee on the Judiciary and its Anti-Trust subcommittee. In this work, Meader tapped his legal experience and became deeply involved in the struggle over the Civil Rights Act of 1964.
After losing his Congressional seat in 1964, Meader returned to the practice of law in Ann Arbor, Michigan and Washington, D.C. He also served as counsel to the Joint Committee on the Organization of Congress. Upon retiring from legal practice, Meader turned to the writing of his memoirs.
George Meader married Elizabeth Faeth in 1928. They had three children: Robert Eugene, Barbara Ellen (who died in 1960), and Catherine Elizabeth.
The George Meader papers primarily document his Congressional service from 1951 to 1964. There are some materials documenting his personal and professional life aside from his work in Congress. The papers relating to Congressional service include correspondence, speeches, campaign literature, texts of radio broadcasts, press releases and newsletters, photographs, and sound recordings. The other materials include memoirs, diaries, correspondence and memoranda, case files, photographs and film, scrapbooks, and correspondence regarding organizations to which Meader belonged and relating to the opening of his Ann Arbor law practice in 1939. Also included in the Meader papers are the diaries, notebooks, and student papers of his daughter, Barbara.
The collection has been divided into five series: the National Defense Investigating Committee, Congressional Files, Personal, Professional, and Visual Materials. The first two series cover Meader's professional activities in Washington, D. C., including what he saw as crucial work on the Truman committee. The original order of material in these series has been pretty much maintained. The next two series, Personal and Professional, reflect the artifice of the archivist as the original order of materials in the groups was significantly altered in the course of processing.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Lawyers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Meader, George, 1907-1994; Republican Party (Mich.); United States. Congress. House.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Government Operations.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on the Judiciary.; United States--Defenses.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Meader, George, 1907-1994; Politics and government.; Travel.; United States. Congress. House.; United States. Congress. Senate.
Subjects - Sound Recordings
Cambodia.; Civil rights--United States.; Discrimination--Law and legislation.; Economic assistance, American.; Elections--United States--1960.; Meader, George, 1907-1994; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Republican Party (Mich.); Taxation--Law and legislation.; United States--Armed Forces--Appropriations and expenditures.; United States. Congress. House.; United States--Politics and government--1953-1961.; United States--Politics and government--1961-1963.; United States--Politics and government--1963-1969.; United States--Foreign economic relations--Cambodia.
Genre/Form:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- National Defense Investigating Committee 1943-1947
  The National Defense Investigating Committee, 1943-1947 series documents Meader's work as counsel for the Truman committee which was charged with seeking out corruption and fraud in defense industries. The series consists of three linear feet of materials arranged alphabetically by type. Of special note are the six folders of Meader's diaries which proffer a detailed daily account of the committee's travels, travails, and investigations.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945, 1947, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Diary May 1945-June 1947, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Notebooks 1945-1946 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1945-1946
    - Bainbridge, MD October 1945 (Box 1)
    - Europe 1945 (Box 1)
    - North Africa 1945-1946 (Box 1)
    - World Trip 1946 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbooks 1945-1947, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Topical Files 1945-1947
    - A (Box 2)
    - Aircraft Report 1948 (Box 2)
    - Assignments 1945-1947 (Box 2)
    - B (Box 2)
    - Basic Magnesium (Box 2)
    - Bilbo, Senator Theodore (Box 2)
    - Brewster, Senator Owen (Box 2)
    - C (Box 2)
    - Cinchona (Box 2)
    - Congressmen (Box 2)
    - D (Box 2)
    - E (Box 2)
    - Executive Sessions (Box 2)
    - F (Box 2)
    - Ferguson, Senator Homer (Box 2)
    - Fifth Annual Report (Box 2)
    - Files (Box 2)
    - Flanagan, Francis (Box 2)
    - Foreign Liquidation Committee (Box 2)
    - Fulton, Hugh (Box 2)
    - G (Box 2)
    - H (Box 2)
    - Halley, Rudolph (Box 2)
    - Hearings (agenda and notes) (Box 2)
    - I (Box 2)
    - Inter-American Highway Report (Box 2)
    - J (Box 2)
    - K (Box 2)
    - Kilgore, Senator Harley (Box 2)
    - Knowland, Senator William (Box 2)
    - L (Box 2)
    - M (Box 2)
    - Memoranda, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Mead, Senator Joseph (Box 2)
    - Military Government (Box 2)
    - N (Box 3)
    - Navy Department (Box 3)
    - Notes (Box 3)
    - O (Box 3)
    - P (Box 3)
    - Press Releases (Box 3)
    - R (Box 3)
    - Resignation of Meader (Box 3)
    - S (Box 3)
    - Senators (Box 3)
    - Speeches, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - State Department (Box 3)
    - Surplus Property Investigation (Box 3)
    - T (Box 3)
    - Transcripts of Testimony (Box 3)
    - Transportation (reports and speech) (Box 3)
    - Truman Committee Demise (Box 3)
    - U-V (Box 3)
    - W (Box 3)
    - War Department (Box 3)
    - World Trip Report (Box 3)
    - X-Y-Z (Box 3)
- Congressional Files 1948-1966
  The bulk of the Meader papers consists of the thirty-three linear feet of materials in the Congressional Files, 1948-1966 series which document his seven terms in the House of Representatives. Subseries are primarily arranged alphabetically by type of material with the exception of the last subseries, Campaign Materials. Materials in these subseries are arranged chronologically by congressional session, then by full committee or subcommittee, finally alphabetically.
  - Annual Files 1954-1964
    The Annual Files subseries comprises fourteen linear feet of correspondence, memoranda, and reports arranged alphabetically by topic, issue, or department within each year. Recurring headings include immigration, the Republican Party, the State Department, Treasury, University of Michigan, and Veterans' Administration.
    - 1954 (A-T) (Box 4)
    - 1954 (U-Z) (Box 5)
    - 1955 (A-Q) (Box 5)
    - 1955 (R-Z) (Box 6)
    - 1956 (A-L) (Box 6)
    - 1956 (M-Z) (Box 7)
    - 1957 (A-D) (Box 7)
    - 1957 (E-Z) (Box 8)
    - 1958 (A-S) (Box 9)
    - 1958 (T-Z) (Box 10)
    - 1959 (A-Q) (Box 10)
    - 1959 (R-Z) (Box 11)
    - 1960 (A-H) (Box 11)
    - 1960 (I-Z) (Box 12)
    - 1961 (A-H) (Box 12)
    - 1961 (I-Z) (Box 13)
    - 1962 (A-C) (Box 13)
    - 1962 (D-Z) (Box 14)
    - 1963 (A-L) (Box 15)
    - 1963 (M-Z) (Box 16)
    - 1964 (A-F) (Box 16)
    - 1964 (G-Z) (Box 17)
  - Government Operations Committee 1951-1964
    - 1951-1956 (Box 18)
    - 1957-1960 (Box 19)
    - 1961-1964 (Box 20)
  - Judiciary Committee 1959-1964
    - 1959-1960 (Box 21)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 22)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 23)
  - Meader Bills and Projects 1951-1966
    By far the most substantive material in the Congressional Files is found in the Meader Bills and Projects subseries. The eight linear feet of material in this subseries is alphabetically arranged by topic, bill, or project. Meader's efforts to insure clean and responsible government are manifest in the Congressional investigation folders and the televised committee hearings materials. District-specific materials can be found in the Great Lakes flood control folders and the material on Monroe.
    - Meader Bills Introduced 1951-1964, 7 folders (Box 24)
    - Audiotapes, 1960-1964
      - Harry Hoke, Jr., inventor, discusses alleged patent infringement, reel-to-reel tape; 3.75 ips (Box 24)
        (tape no. 1)
      - Meader addresses Washtenaw Republicans August 10, 1960, reel-to-reel tape; 7.5 ips (Box 24)
        (tape no. 2)
      - Meader introduction of Richard Nixon in Monroe, Michigan October 27, 1960, reel-to-reel tape; 3.75 ips (Box 24)
        (tape no. 3)
      - Meader discusses foreign aid to Cambodia March 15, 1962, reel-to-reel tape; 7.5 ips (Box 24)
        (tape no. 4)
      - Meader criticizes tax law April 6, 1962, reel-to-reel tape; 7.5 ips (Box 24)
        (tape no. 5)
      - Meader on defense appropriations bill to WWJ's "Capitol Report" April 20, 1962, reel-to-reel tape; 7.5 ips (Box 24)
        (tape no. 6)
      - Meader on defense appropriations bill April 27, 1962, reel-to-reel tape; 7.5 ips (Box 24)
        (tape no. 7)
      - Meader resolution on telecasting of House committee hearings January 14, 1963, reel-to-reel tape; 7.5 ips (Box 24)
        (tape no. 8)
      - Meader discusses vote against Civil Rights Bill April 30, 1964, reel-to-reel tape; 7.5 ips (Box 24)
        (tape no. 9)
    - Bonner Military Supply Investigation 1951, 22 folders (Box 24)
    - Bridgeport Brass Co. 1959-1961, 2 folders (Box 25)
    - Brownson Committee Trip/Investigation 1953-1954, 17 folders (Box 25)
    - Civil Rights 1961-1964, 18 folders (Box 26)
    - Congressional Committee Staffing 1952-1961 (Box 26)
    - Congressional Investigation Function 1953-1961 (Box 26)
    - Dundee Cement Co. 1958-1960, 3 folders (Box 26)
    - Excise Tax 1953-1956, 3 folders (Box 26)
    - Executive Privilege 1959-1962, 2 folders (Box 26)
    - Executive Reorganization Act 1957-1958, 2 folders (Box 26)
    - Gerity Magnesium/United States Air Force 1956-1957, 5 folders (Box 27)
    - Government Research Commission 1961-1964, 2 folders (Box 27)
    - Great Lakes Flood Control 1951-1964, 11 folders (Box 27)
    - Investigations 1951-1952
      - Government Corruption (Box 27)
      - Justice Department (Box 27)
      - Mutual Security (Box 27)
      - Post Office Department (Box 27)
      - State Department (Box 27)
    - Joint Committee on Organization of Congress 1966 (Box 28)
    - Liu Immigration Case 1952-1954, 2 folders (Box 28)
    - Monroe Atomic Plant 1956-1962, 4 folders (Box 28)
    - Monroe Land Patent 1953-1959 (Box 28)
    - Monroe Port Bill 1951-1964, 5 folders (Box 28)
    - National Family Day 1956-1959, 2 folders (Box 28)
    - Newspapers and Antitrust Laws 1951-1960, 5 folders (Box 28)
    - Overseas Investment 1951-1964, 8 folders (Box 29)
    - Payment in Lieu of Taxes 1953-1964, 6 folders (Box 29)
    - State Tax Use 1957-1960, 3 folders (Box 29)
    - Televised Committee Hearings 1951-1964, 7 folders (Box 30)
    - Trips
      - 1953-1955, 13 folders (Box 30)
      - 1956-1964, 9 folders (Box 31)
    - Unemployment and IMC Copper 1951-1952 (Box 31)
    - University of Michigan Towing 1961-1962 (Box 31)
    - Willow Run Airport 1955-1964, 8 folders (Box 31)
    - Miscellaneous 1951-1964, 8 folders (Box 31)
  - Topical Files 1951-1964
    The Topical Files subseries consists of one linear foot of miscellaneous office files arranged alphabetically. The folders on Republican voting trends for Michigan, 1941-1960 are of special interest.
    - Newsletters 1951-1964, 14 folders (Box 32)
    - Press Releases 1951-1964, 14 folders (Box 32)
    - Radio/Television 1951-1964, 14 folders (Box 32)
    - Republican Voting Trends 1960, 3 folders (Box 32)
  - Campaign Files 1948-1966
    The Campaign Files subseries consists of four linear feet of correspondence and memos, financial files, reports and background, and sundry campaign literature. These materials are arranged chronologically, within each campaign year, they are alphabetically arranged.
    - 1948 (A-Z), 7 folders (Box 33)
    - 1950 (A-Z), 17 folders (Box 33)
    - 1952 (A-Z), 5 folders (Box 33)
    - 1954 (A-Z), 3 folders (Box 33)
    - 1956 (A-Z), 5 folders (Box 34)
    - 1958 (A-Z), 8 folders (Box 34)
    - 1960 (A-Z), 22 folders (Box 34)
    - 1962
      - District Office (A-Z), 13 folders (Box 35)
      - Washington Office (A-Z), 13 folders (Box 35)
    - 1964
      - Primary Election (A-Z), 35 folders (Box 35)
      - General Election (A-Z), 23 folders (Box 36)
    - 1966 (A-Z), 24 folders (Box 36)
- Personal 1922-1990
  The Personal series is comprised of memoirs and genealogical materials, correspondence, financial files, writings (of George Meader, his daughter, and his wife), and a brief exchange of letters between Meader and the Detroit Automobile Inter-Insurance Exchange regarding and attempt in 1940 to cancel his policy. This polymorphic series runs two linear feet. Meader's memoirs provide a nostalgic impression of his early years as a student, seaman, Ann Arbor attorney and active member of local civic organizations, and general counsel to the Truman committee. Meader's views on government can be gleaned from his trenchant essays found in the Writings subseries. Barbara Meader's writings provide a fascinating glimpse into the mind of a young woman coming into her maturity at the University of Michigan in the late 1950s. This glimpse is rendered poignant by her untimely death shortly before graduating.
  - Memoirs 1989-1990
    - Early Years 1920s-1943, 2 folders (Box 37)
    - The Truman Committee 1943-1947, 3 folders (Box 37)
  - Genealogy 1940-1989
    - Gibson Family 1980s (Box 37)
    - Meader Family (Robert Eugene) 1940s (Box 37)
    - Meader Family Association 1976-1989 (Box 37)
  - Correspondence 1922-1980s
    - Detroit Automobile Inter-Insurance Exchange 1940 (Box 37)
      (re: cancellation of Meader's insurance policy)
    - Meader, Barbara 1951-1960, 3 folders (Box 37)
    - Meader, Edwin 1943-1965 (Box 37)
    - Meader, Elizabeth 1944-1965 (Box 37)
    - Meader, Katherine 1958-1968, 3 folders (Box 37)
    - Meader, R. Paul 1945-1965 (Box 37)
    - Meader, Ralph 1943-1964 (Box 37)
    - Meader, Robert Eugene 1946-1952 (Box 37)
    - Meader, Mrs. R. E. (Jean) 1952-1961 (Box 37)
    - Meader Way, Frances 1922-1975 (Box 37)
    - Miscellaneous 1964-1980s, 4 folders (Box 37)
  - Financial 1939-1990
    - General 1939-1943, 1965-1966, 2 folders (Box 37)
    - Income Tax 1942-1954 (Box 37)
    - Income Tax 1955-1963, 2 folders (Box 38)
    - Loans 1943-1956 (Box 38)
    - Property 1937-1947, 2 folders (Box 38)
    - Will 1984-1990 (Box 38)
  - Organizations 1937-1940
    - Ann Arbor Junior Chamber of Commerce 1937-1939 (Box 38)
    - Michigan Merit System Association 1938-1939 (Box 38)
    - University of Michigan Alumni Association 9th District 1938-1940 (Box 38)
  - Writings 1952-1990
    - Barbara Meader 1952-1960
      - Diaries 1952-1958 (Box 38)
      - University of Michigan 1958-1960, 2 folders (Box 38)
      - Miscellaneous 1960 (Box 38)
    - Elizabeth Meader 1958-1966 (Box 38)
    - George Meader 1964-1990
      - Federal Encroachment on Congress 1966 (Box 38)
      - Congressional Reform 1967-1970 (Box 38)
      - Litigation and Congress 1968-1974 (Box 38)
      - Iran Contra Affair 1987 (Box 38)
      - Miscellaneous 1964-1990, 2 folders (Box 38)
- Professional 1933-1974
  The Professional series has been divided into two subseries. The Law Practice subseries contains files from the 1992 accession regarding Meader's early law practice in Ann Arbor. The Law Cases subseries consists of two distinct, but related, sets of files, linked to Meader's practice of law. This series runs four linear feet and contains two alphabetical runs of case files from Meader's law practice, one covering the years before his Congressional service and one covering his post-Congressional practice. The latter includes files related to Meader's involvement in the 1968 suit brought before the U.S. Supreme Court by Adam Clayton Powell, contesting his expulsion by the U.S. House of Representatives. The first set of case files provide a unique perspective on postwar Ann Arbor through the records of a small town lawyer.
  - Law Practice 1933-1940
    - Law Office, Establishment 1939-1940 (Box 38)
    - Law Office, Financial 1933-1938 (Box 38)
  - Law Cases, Pre-Congressional 1946-1956
    - Aiken Estate (Box 38)
    - Ann Arbor Press v. NLRB (Box 38)
    - Ann Arbor Press v. NLRB (cont.), 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Buchanan, Mary (Box 39)
    - Columbian Wire Corporation (Box 39)
    - Congressional Investigation, 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Dearborn Diecasting and Cavity Corporation (Box 39)
    - Dexter Machine Products, 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Dexter Savings Bank (Box 39)
    - Dunn, Brent (Box 39)
    - Eichholz, Albert (Box 39)
    - Exhibition Ships, Inc. (Box 39)
    - Full Salvation Union v. Portage Township (Box 39)
    - Gucker, Frank (Box 39)
    - Hermann Estate (Box 39)
    - Hickenlooper, Senator Bowers (Box 39)
    - Higgins, Inc. (Box 39)
    - Kamman, Francis (Box 39)
    - Kauffman v. Shidakar (Box 39)
    - Leavell, John (Box 39)
    - Lefurge, William (Box 39)
    - Locke, Edward (Box 39)
    - Macintosh (Box 39)
    - Machinery Brief (Box 39)
    - Mead, Senator Joseph (Box 39)
    - Meader and Kamman Partnership (Box 39)
    - Meikle, D. G., 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Michigan State Society (Box 40)
    - Occident Orient Corporation, 2 folders (Box 40)
    - Parker-Nashville Commodities (Box 40)
    - Por, John Leslie, 2 folders (Box 40)
    - Preuss, Lawrence (Box 40)
    - Prosecutor Campaign (Meader) (Box 40)
    - Reconstruction Finance Corporation, 5 folders (Box 40)
    - Rives Plating Corporation (Box 40)
    - Roberts, John (Box 40)
    - Vandenberg, Senator Arthur (Box 40)
    - Vitoganis, Gus (Box 40)
    - Wallgren, M. C. (Box 40)
    - Waltz, Stanley G. (Box 40)
    - WPAG (Box 40)
    - Yale Rubber Company (Box 40)
  - Law Cases, Post-Congressional 1966-1974 (fragmentary)
    - Marston v. Ann Arbor Property Managers (Box 40)
    - Matthaei, Fred (Box 40)
    - Meader, Brimacombe, & Schleter (Box 40)
    - Michigan v. Fruehauf, 2 folders (Box 41)
    - Michigan v. Landa (Box 41)
    - Niedemeyer v. Ford (Box 41)
    - Nixon Pardon (Box 41)
    - Pepaja v. Burger King (Box 41)
    - Powell (Adam Clayton Powell) Hearings 1967-1968
      - Supreme Court no. 138 (Box 41)
      - Certiori Petition (Box 41)
      - Clippings (Box 41)
      - Court of Appeals, 5 folders (Box 41)
      - Curtis Law Review, 2 folders (Box 41)
      - District Court, 5 folders (Box 41)
      - Fourteenth Amendment (Box 41)
      - Notes/Background, 4 folders (Box 42)
      - Select Committee (Box 42)
    - Seaway Associates (Box 42)
    - Smith, Leila Riley (Box 42)
    - Spindler (Box 42)
    - Trogdon v. Archer (Box 42)
    - Union Central (Box 42)
    - Unitec (Box 42)
    - Zahn v. Smith (Box 42)
- Visual Materials
  Portraits; photographs of congressional colleagues and other politicians; photographs, 1945-1946, of travels to Europe and North Africa with the U.S. Senate National Defense Investigating Committee; and films of Meader and colleagues discussing issues of foreign and domestic policy.
  - Photographs
    - Portraits, 2 folders (Box 42)
      (also oversize folder UAm)
    - Family Portraits (Box 42)
    - Family, Informal (Box 42)
    - Congressional, 3 folders (Box 42)
    - Michigan Congressmen (autographed) (Box 42)
    - Michigan Politicians (Box 42)
    - United States Senators (autographed) (Box 42)
  - Films (Congress), 1962, 5 reels
    - Urban Affairs (Box 42)
    - Cambodia (Box 42)
    - Tax Bill (Box 42)
    - "White House Conference on the New Frontier" and "Defense Appropriations Bill" (Box 42)
    - Defense Department Budget